<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<site
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="index.xsd"
    >
    <studio source="https://www.paradoxinteractive.com/our-games/discover">
        <studio_description>
            <title>Paradox Interactive</title>
            <studio_history>Paradox Interactive AB is a video game publisher based in Stockholm, Sweden. The company started out as the video game division of Target Games and then Paradox Entertainment (now Cabinet Entertainment) before being spun out into an independent company in 2004. Through a combination of expanding internal studios, founding new studios and purchasing independent developers, the company has grown to comprise nine first-party development studios, including their flagship Paradox Development Studio, and acts as publisher for games from other developers. Paradox is best known for releasing historically themed strategy video games, especially grand strategy games, and has published strategy games in different settings, as well as games of other genres such as role-playing video games and management simulators. They typically continue development of their games after initial release with the creation of downloadable content, and are also known for creating games that are easy to mod. Outside of video games, Paradox has created board games based on several of its titles, and owns the rights to the tabletop role-playing game series World of Darkness since purchasing White Wolf Publishing in 2015. They hold an annual convention, PDXCon, which has been open to the public since 2017.</studio_history>
            
        </studio_description>
        <beggining>2004</beggining>
    </studio>

    <photo_galery>
        <photo number="1" games_list="Europa Universalis IV">./img/Eu4map.jpg</photo>
        <photo number="2" games_list="Crusader Kings III">./img/ck3map.jpg</photo>
        <photo number="3" games_list="Hearts Of Iron IV">./img/Hoi4map.jpg</photo>
        <photo number="4" games_list="Victoria III">./img/victoria3map.avif</photo>
    </photo_galery>


    <games>
        <game release="2013">
            <title>Europa Universalis IV</title>
            <about>
                <development>Early design discussions for Europa Universalis IV began shortly after the December 2010 release of Divine Wind, the final DLC for Europa Universalis III[5] with development, based on the Clausewitz Engine, beginning in earnest in about September 2011. It was first announced to the public in August 2012, to coincide with a showing at that year's Gamescom, after having been teased under the codename of "Project Truman". Throughout the game's development, Paradox Development Studio released weekly "developer diaries" via their online forums, in which they detailed some feature of the game's development. These included information about design philosophy, game mechanisms that were being implemented, and features from Europa Universalis III that were being removed. During its development, Europa Universalis IV had a greater priority given to stability and quality control than had previous games in the series. There had previously been a perception that Paradox's games were not worth buying until several updates or expansions had fixed stability issues. Studio CEO, Fredrik Wester, described this perception as being like "a slap in the face", motivating them to improve. Another of Paradox's major goals was to retain the depth and complexity of their earlier grand strategy games, while making them easier for a player to interact with. Prior to release, a preview version of the game was showcased through Let's Plays[citation needed] and via a multiplayer event for journalists. A playable demo of the game was released on Steam on 9 August 2013 with the game itself being released on 13 August. Following its release, development of the game has continued under the same model that Paradox had previously used successfully for Crusader Kings II, with paid DLCs being released alongside, and helping to fund, additional free patches which add more features to the base game. As of November 2021, eighteen expansions have been released for the game alongside many minor DLCs offering additional graphical or musical options. In September 2020, Paradox Tinto, a newly formed division of Paradox, took over development of the game led by leader Johan Andersson. This team released the expansions Leviathan and Origins, while also focusing on bug fixes and eventually ending development on the game.</development>
                <gameplay>The game has been formed to begin historically, with events occurring when they did in history. The game itself is an interactive map of Earth divided into the provinces that compose nations. Each of these provinces contribute to their country either positively or negatively, as provinces can both provide resources to a nation and serve as a point of unrest and rebellion. The gameplay requires the player to lead a nation by finding a balance of military, diplomacy, and economy. The player does so through their choices as sovereign of their nation, and through the spending of resources available to them: prestige, power projection, stability, gold (ducats), manpower, legitimacy for monarchies, republican tradition for republics, devotion for theocracies, horde unity for steppe nomads, meritocracy for celestial empires, and monarch power (administrative, diplomatic, and military). Players can choose to conquer the world by military might, become a colonial superpower, establish trade dominance, etc. as one of over 500 different nations. These nations range alphabetically from Aachen to Zuni. The game is a sandbox environment, and while there is no strict rule on winning the game, the game of the player is over when the player's nation is removed, or annexed, from the map. Diplomacy is a large aspect of the game, as creating alliances, (or vassal states and tributaries), improving opinions, and preventing defensive coalitions are vital to a player's survival. Espionage can also be employed against enemy states in order to claim their territory, or incite rebellion in their provinces, along with other dubious ends. Combat can be waged on both land and sea, during which the game attempts to simulate real world factors such as morale, discipline, varying unit types with associated strengths and weaknesses, competency of leaders, terrain and supply lines. Trade is also an important part of the game, where the world is divided into many trade nodes and trade flows through each of the nodes and can be collected by merchants. Many major religions, such as Catholic, Orthodox, Protestant, Sunni, and Shia are present in the game and can provide distinct bonuses to their practitioners. Players can employ missionaries to convert their provinces or can engage in policies of universal religious freedom. For example, the Catholic faith makes use of the Papacy, which can allow a nation to have control over the Pope or to use their influence for other rewards. Native American and Aboriginal religions are also present in the game, most commonly utilizing a system of selecting a bonus for the lifetime of the present monarch. Furthermore, many of the world's institutions, from feudalism to industrialization, are also present in the game. Institutions normally begin around a certain year, and begin spreading through provinces. The rate of institution spread and where the institution spawns is malleable to player actions. The institution coincides with increasing the price of technology, as the lack of an embraced institution increases the cost of corresponding technological levels. Once reaching requirements, usually consisting of a ducat cost and a certain amount of institution present in the player's provinces, the player is able to embrace the institution. An embracement gives an institution-specific nation bonus, as well as purging any technological maluses that the lack of institution may have incurred. Technological advancements are invested in over time, and require the expense of monarch points. They provide benefits to the nation as detailed below: Administrative technology unlocks advancements such as increased productivity, new forms of government, new buildings, and the national idea system. Diplomatic technology unlocks advancements such as naval units, improvements in trade, new buildings, and improved colonial expansion. Military technology unlocks advancements such as new types of land units, improved unit morale, combat tactics, and new buildings. Gameplay is influenced by random events that arise every so often for the player. These events can be either helpful or harmful. Some of these random events are driven by an individual country's history, while some can apply to any country and serve generally to enhance the "flavor" of the game. Some events are also motivated by various institutions that occur throughout the history of the game, such as the Industrial Revolution. Players can choose to play single player mode versus the AI, or multiplayer over a LAN or the Internet against a mix of human and AI opponents. Single player also has the option of "Ironman" mode, which locks several settings such as difficulty, and removes the control of saving the game from the player. This means that any mistakes are irreversible. It is, however, the only way to receive any of the game's many achievements.</gameplay>
                <legacy>Europa Universalis was the first in the series, followed by Europa Universalis II, Europa Universalis III, Europa Universalis: Rome and Europa Universalis IV.</legacy>
            </about>
            <time>
                <start era="AD">1444</start>
                <end era="AD">1821</end>
            </time>
            <wiki_link wiki="https://eu4.paradoxwikis.com/Europa_Universalis_4_Wiki">Europa Universalis wiki</wiki_link>
        </game>
        <game release="2020">
            <title>Crusader Kings III</title>
            <about>
                <development>Game director Henrik Fåhraeus commented that development of the game commenced "about 1 year before Imperator", indicating a starting time of 2015. Describing the game engine of Crusader Kings II as cobbled and "held together with tape", he explained that the new game features an updated engine (i.e. Clausewitz Engine + Jomini toolset) with more power to run new features. As is the case with many of Paradox's unreleased and currently supported works, the developers publish a weekly developer diary. Each post focuses on a single aspect of the game, such as government types, user interface, governments, war, etc., how this aspect of the game will be handled in Crusader Kings III, and how it is different from Crusader Kings II. A monthly update video is also published on the Paradox Interactive YouTube channel, summarising all of the changes which have been made in that month's Dev Diaries.</development>
                <gameplay>Like its predecessors Crusader Kings and Crusader Kings II, Crusader Kings III is a grand strategy game and dynasty simulator set in the Middle Ages. Players begin as a character in either 867 or 1066. The game map is about four times more detailed than the one in Crusader Kings II and slightly larger, incorporating Europe, Africa roughly as far south as the Equator, and Asia as far East as Tibet. Upon the death or deposition of a player's character they may continue to play as that character's heir. Overall, players develop a dynasty over the centuries, with the game ending in 1453. Dynasties can form cadet branches that have their own heads and act mostly independently from their parent dynasty. The heads of dynasties are able to use a new resource known as Renown to assert their control over their house. For example, the heads of houses are responsible for legitimizing bastards. Characters have full-body, 3D-rendered character models instead of 2D portraits. As in Crusader Kings II, they have traits that affect their stats and behavior. Making choices that go against a character's traits will increase that character's stress. The game's genetics system allows characters to pass on some of their characteristics to their descendants. Characters are able to frighten their vassals into staying loyal by increasing their Dread, which increases when the character performs malevolent actions, such as executing or torturing other characters.Characters are able to select one of five lifestyles to follow. Each lifestyle has three skill trees that allow characters to enhance skills related to that lifestyle. Players' realms may have the feudal, tribal, or clan government types.[ Religion and culture are both aspects of the game. Leaders can advance their goals by warfare, diplomacy, or subterfuge. Players may undergo pilgrimages and wage holy wars, and entire religions can be called to arms in crusades or jihads. Religions have Tenets, which are bonuses given to all practitioners of that faith, and Doctrines, which deal with the religion's stances towards issues like homosexuality and female clergy.[9] The principle resource for interacting with religion mechanics is Piety, and a player with sufficient piety may choose to develop their own heresy, with the Tenets and Doctrines being chosen by the player. Levies are represented primarily by low-quality infantry composed of peasants. Characters will need to hire men-at-arms in order to field higher-quality soldiers, such as crossbowmen and cavalry. Characters can make other characters from their court or realm with significant combat skills into powerful knights.</gameplay>
                <legacy>Crusader Kings was the first in the series, followed by Crusader Kings II Dark Ages, Crusader Kings III.</legacy>
            </about>
            <time>
                <start era="AD">1066</start>
                <end era="AD">1453</end>
            </time>
            <wiki_link wiki="https://ck3.paradoxwikis.com/Crusader_Kings_III_Wiki">Crusader Kings III wiki</wiki_link>
        </game>
        <game release="2016">
            <title>Hearts Of Iron IV</title>
            <about>
                <development>Hearts of Iron IV was announced in 2014 and was originally slated for a late 2015 release. At E3 2015, creative director Johan Andersson confirmed that the game would be pushed back from its original release window, with the new release date being scheduled for the first quarter of 2016. This was an attempt to resolve several issues encountered with the game. In March 2016, it was announced that the game, built with the Clausewitz Engine, would be released on 6 June 2016, which was the 72nd anniversary of the Normandy landings.</development>
                <gameplay>Hearts of Iron IV is a grand strategy wargame that primarily revolves around World War II. The player may play as any nation in the world in the 1936 or 1939 start dates in singleplayer or multiplayer, although the game is not designed to go beyond 1950. A nation's military is divided between naval forces, aerial forces, and ground forces. For the ground forces, the player may train, customize, and command divisions consisting of various types of infantry, tanks, and other units. These divisions require equipment and manpower to fight properly. The navy and air force also require men and equipment, including the actual warships and warplanes that are used in combat. Equipment is produced by military factories, while ships are built by dockyards. These military factories and dockyards are, in turn, constructed by civilian factories, which also construct a variety of other buildings, produce consumer goods for the civilian population, and oversee commerce with other nations. Most nations are initially forced to devote a significant number of their civilian factories to producing consumer goods, but as the nation becomes increasingly mobilized, more factories will be freed up for other purposes. Mobilization is represented as a "policy" that the player may adjust with the proper amount of political power, an abstract "resource" that is also used to appoint new ministers and change other facets of the nation's government. In addition to mobilization, there are other policies, including the nation's stance on conscription and commerce. Land in Hearts of Iron IV is divided into tiny regions known as provinces (also called tiles), which are grouped to form states. Each state has a certain amount of building slots, factory slots, and 5 infrastructure slots. The major seas and oceans (for warships) and the sky (for warplanes) are similarly divided into different regions. These provinces each have a type of terrain assigned to them that determines how well different types of units will perform in combat there. Divisions are placed in provinces and can attack enemy units in adjacent provinces. How well divisions perform in combat depends on various factors, such as the quality of their equipment, the weather, the type of terrain, the skill and traits of the general commanding the divisions, aerial combat in the region and the morale of both sides. Technologies can be researched to improve equipment. Military doctrines can be upgraded by using army XP, among other things, which often means that a more technologically advanced nation will have an edge in combat. If a division (or a group of divisions) successfully overwhelms an enemy province, they may occupy it. Some provinces may have victory points, which can push a nation closer towards capitulation if occupied. Occupying key provinces within a state allows the occupying power to access the enemy's factories and natural resources in that state. Resistance to occupation within a state can hamper the occupying power's control over it. Late in the game, nations may develop nuclear bombs if they have the proper technology, which can be used to devastate enemy provinces and states. Hearts of Iron IV also attempts to recreate the complex diplomatic relationships of the day. Nations may undertake a variety of diplomatic actions; they may sign non-aggression pacts, guarantee the independence of other nations, and offer or request military access, amongst other things. Another key feature of diplomacy is the ability to create a faction or invite other nations to an existing one. Factions represent the main alliances of the era, like the Axis and Allies (for gameplay purposes, real-world factions like the Axis and Allies are split into numerous smaller factions, like the Comintern, the Chinese United Front, and the Co-Prosperity Sphere). Faction members may assist each other in wars, making faction members precious assets. Some more clandestine diplomatic actions are also available. For example, the player may justify war against other nations, spread their ideology abroad, or stage a coup. Countries in the game may be democratic, fascist, communist, or non-aligned. Each of the four ideologies has advantages and disadvantages; for example, fascist nations can go to war with other countries easily, but other nations are not as willing to trade with them as they are with democratic countries. If a different ideology becomes too popular in a country, a referendum may be held that will peacefully convert the nation to the most popular ideology. Otherwise, ideologies may come to power violently through coups, civil wars, or forced subjugation by a foreign power. This diplomacy is further expanded through the addition of espionage in the expansion La Résistance, which extends gameplay in the management of occupied territories which is done differently according to player choices and ideology. Furthermore, the operation of spy networks allows nations to steal technology, gather information on an opponents's military, and engage in other espionage efforts. While Hearts of Iron IV does feature some scripted events, the game features a "national focus" system that makes fixed events less necessary than in previous installments in the series. Each country in the game has a "focus tree" with various "national focuses" that grant certain effects or trigger events. For example, for the Anschluss to occur, Germany must first complete the focus that is related to it. Other focuses can grant special bonuses, like faster research times for certain technologies or extra factories. While some bonuses (like extra factories) are very tangible, others (like improvements to morale) are more abstract. These abstract bonuses are represented by "national spirits" that can be temporary or permanent. Not all national spirits are granted by focuses, and not all spirits are entirely beneficial. Focuses are completed over time; only one focus may be worked on at once, and working on one consumes some political power. Initially, only a handful of key nations, like Nazi Germany, the United Kingdom, the Soviet Union, and the United States, had unique focus trees; all other nations shared a generic one. Subsequent updates and DLCs have added focus trees to other nations as well. Hearts of Iron IV also introduces the concept of "world tension," an abstract representation of how close the world is to global war, on a scale from 0 to 100. Aggressive actions by any nation can increase world tension, while peaceful actions can decrease it. Depending on the circumstances of a nation, like their ideology, a certain level of world tension may be necessary to perform certain actions, like justifying war against another country.</gameplay>
                <legacy>Hearts of Iron was the first in the series, followed by Hearts of Iron II, Hearts of Iron III and Hearts of Iron IV.</legacy>
            </about>
            <time>
                <start era="AD">1936</start>
                <end era="AD">1948</end>
            </time>
            <wiki_link wiki="https://hoi4.paradoxwikis.com/Hearts_of_Iron_4_Wiki">Hearts Of Iron IV wiki</wiki_link>
            </game>
            <game release="2022">
                <title>Victoria III</title>
                <about>
                    <development>In the lead up to the game's announcement, Victoria III was seen as a meme by the Paradox fanbase due to players constantly asking about it, only to be ignored, with many joking that it would never see a release or that any mention of the number 'three' from an official Paradox source meant that the game was on the way. Martin "Wiz" Anward served as director of the game's development. In April 2022, a beta version of the game was leaked online.</development>
                    <gameplay>Victoria III spans world history from 1836 to 1936 and allows the player to control any one of over 100 countries that existed during that time period. The game focuses on politics and demographics, with gameplay focusing on appealing to and appeasing population groups ("pops"), large blocks of people with shared interests. Pops possess a variety of interests with different ideologies that the player deals with. Another system in the game is Diplomatic Plays, which borrows heavily from Victoria II's crisis system. When attempting to force other countries to concede land or open markets, players will present a target country with a demand detailing what they desire, which will result in the target country having the opportunity to demand concessions from the aggressor. Following this exchange of demands, a timer will begin counting down as both sides have a chance to mobilize troops and attract potential allies by offering spoils. If no diplomatic resolution is reached before the timer runs out, war will be declared. Designer Mikael Andersson explained that this system was designed with the intent to tone down the role of warfare by making diplomacy equally as capable.</gameplay>
                    <legacy>Victoria was the first in the series, followed by Victoria II, Victoria III.</legacy>
                </about>
                <time>
                    <start era="AD">1836</start>
                    <end era="AD">1936</end>
                </time>
                <wiki_link wiki="https://vic3.paradoxwikis.com/Victoria_3_Wiki">Victoria III wiki</wiki_link>
            </game>
    </games>
    <links>
        <link>../HTML_CSS/eu.html</link>
        <link>../HTML_CSS/ck.html</link>
        <link>../HTML_CSS/hoi.html</link>
        <link>../HTML_CSS/victoria.html</link>
    </links>
    <Game_sold>
        <headlines>
            Game
            Sold
        </headlines>
        <game_name>
            Europa Universalis IV 5000000
            Crusader Kings III	5000000
            Victoria III	1000000
            Hearts of Iron IV	10000000
        </game_name>
    </Game_sold>
    
    <stock_value currency="EUR">
        <studio_name>Paradox Interactive</studio_name>
        <value>201.30</value>
    </stock_value>

    <sources>
        <source_title source="https://pl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Strona_g%C5%82%C3%B3wna">Wikipedia</source_title>
        
    </sources>

    <author>
        <name age="19">Artur</name>
        <surname>Binczyk</surname>
    </author>

</site>